<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two letters: the first, being a relation of a sad accident that fell out at Erpingham neer Norwich July 2. shewing how a fire-ball fell from the heavens into the parish church there, broke down part of the steeple and several places in the church-wall, kill'd one man and wounded diverse, &amp;c. The second, being a relation of a strange sight in the heavens, seen by three justices of the peace their sons. Dated, Hungerford in Wiltshire, June 19. 1665.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3479A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896033</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896033</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2374:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two letters: the first, being a relation of a sad accident that fell out at Erpingham neer Norwich July 2. shewing how a fire-ball fell from the heavens into the parish church there, broke down part of the steeple and several places in the church-wall, kill'd one man and wounded diverse, &amp;c. The second, being a relation of a strange sight in the heavens, seen by three justices of the peace their sons. Dated, Hungerford in Wiltshire, June 19. 1665.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for L. Chapman in Exchange-Alley, in Corn hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item is uncut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Natural disasters --  England --  Erpingham --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meteorites --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153700:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
            <p>TWO LETTERS: THE Firſt, being a Relation of a Sad Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that Fell Out at Erpingham NEER NORWICH, <hi>July</hi> 2. Shewing how a Fire-Ball fell from the Heavens into the Pariſh Church there, Broke down part of the Steeple and ſeveral places in the Church-wall, kill'd one man and wounded diverſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Second, Being a Relation of a ſtrange Sight in the Heavens, ſeen by Three Juſtices of the Peace their Sons. Dated, <hi>Hungerford</hi> in <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> June 19. 1665.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for L. <hi>Chapman</hi> in <hi>Exchange-Alley,</hi> in <hi>Corn hill,</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:153700:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:153700:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
            <head>The Firſt being a Relation of a Sad Accident, That fell out at <hi>Erpingham</hi> neer <hi>Norwich, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Norwich</hi> 
                  <date>4. <hi>July</hi> 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THe laſt Lords Day, as Maſter <hi>Hobbs</hi> was Preaching in his Pariſh Church of <hi>Erpingham</hi> in the After-noon, there did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe a great Storm, and there deſcended a great Grey Ball, which they within did conclude did beat down the South-weſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Steeple towards the top of it, (for that was beaten down) then it fell and turned in at the South-Porch, and as ſoon as the ſaid Ball was come into the Church, it turned upon the South-ſide, on which ſide were the mens Seats, and Maſter <hi>Hobbs</hi> being in the Pulpit did ſee the men fall ſome back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſome forwards from their Seats, that
<pb facs="tcp:153700:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->he thought that they had been all ſtruck dead, it went towards the Chancel and broke. Upon which, the Church was as if it had been all of a Fire, and left a great ſmoak and ſtinke behinde it, and upon the breaking there was a great and hedious out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry in the Church: And in the Concluſion, there was but one man found ſtark Dead, but many others lamed, and ſo do yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue; and one Woman who ſat in the Porch is ſo weak, as it is thought ſhe will not live; It did Raſe and Tare the Church-wall in two places within: Maſter <hi>Houſe</hi> is one that is Lame, who ſate above towards the Chancel, and about the top of his Thigh in the Croine of his Body, is a round red place, and down from that about the breadth of a Finger a red place to his Foot, which is very painfull, and his ſtocking within ſide is feared and not without.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:153700:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <head>The Second, being a Relation of a ſtrange Sight in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Loving Son and Daughter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Kinde Loves to you, and we are glad to heare of your good health, as we are at preſent: We have great cauſe to bleſſe God for his great loving kindeneſſes to us, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath given us ſo large a time to Repent in: God grant we may ſo doe, that we may be a people prepared for our Lord.</p>
            <p>Children, I have received two Letters from you, which doth let us underſtand, that you are not minded to ſtay long in <hi>London;</hi> Daughter, if your Heart faile you, pray come to us with ſpeed, for I am afraid Gods Hand is heavy upon <hi>London,</hi> for our Sins and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:153700:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->are very great, and there are Three ſorts of Judgements pointing at us; Famine of Soul and Body, Sword and Pestilence. Good Children make haſt (and let every faithful Soul, I ſay to you, Remember <hi>Lot,</hi> how he was thruſt out of <hi>Sodome</hi>) and come to us; And I ſay, as <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaid to <hi>Naomi,</hi> Come let us Dye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for ſurely the Lord hath ſome great thing to do; for elſe he would not have appeared ſo to many as he hath done.</p>
            <p>Children, I let you underſtand of a true and strange thing: God hath appeared to Three Sons of Three Juſtices of Peace, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hard by us, and ſome you know: Theſe three went to School at <hi>Ward;</hi> and as they were together the <hi>11th</hi> day of <hi>June</hi> last, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Sunſet, or a little after, a Light ſhone on one of them, and he looked up to Heaven, and fell to the Earth on his back, holding out his Hands to Heaven, and was not able to move himſelf nor ſpeake: The Second ſaid, <hi>Let us go and call him,</hi> but he moved not; ſo the ſecond looked up, and he fell on his back, holding out his hands toward Heaven; and the
<pb facs="tcp:153700:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->third did ſo likewiſe: and looking up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they ſaw the Skye open and Heaven, and a great round Circle like a great Well's mouth, and a Coffin paſſe in it, and a long Head, and very long Haire, and it paſſed by; and then they ſaw Three Coffins more, and three Bodies lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Hands from their knees toward their Mouths up and down, as though they were ſtrong in Prayer, and Wrastling with God, and then paſſed by; And then Three glorious men did Appear, as glorious as Angels, and they fell from Heaven to Earth, not far from them; and they were ſore amazed, and not quite well yet. And one of the Juſtices went and Commanded theſe Three apart, and they ſpake as one Mouth, theſe Three Sonnes: One was Eight years old the other Two about Thirteen or Fourteen years old.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Tho. Goddard, Hungerford</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune 19. 1665.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153700:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
